Guide to the Weaver Social History Collection, 1913-1970 AIS.1964.19
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Weaver Social History Collection
1913-1970
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Weaver, John C.
AIS.1964.19
115 Linear Feet (104 boxes)
The Weaver Social History Collection contains correspondence, memorabilia, newspapers and pamphlets of discussion and action groups interested in economic, social, and labor problems in Pittsburgh and Western Pennsylvania within a national and international scope from 1913 to 1970.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Weaver on February 26, 1964, April 22, 1969, and August 23, 1977.
Previous Citation
Weaver Social History Collection, 1913-1970, AIS.1964.19, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into nine series:
Series I. Hungry Club
Series II. University Extension Service
Series III. Council for Peace and Social Action
Series IV. Joint Committee on the Social Crisis
Series V. League for Social Justice
Series VI. ACLU
Series VII. Weaver Correspondence
Series VIII. Assorted Publications
Series IX. Allegheny Roundtable
Scope and Content Notes
The Weaver Social History Collection was created by John C. Weaver, a former social worker turned peace activist. Weaver's active interest in social issues, politics, and world events led him to accumulate a massive amount of research material during his lifetime. This collection reflects his interest in economic, social, and labor issues and problems in Pittsburgh and Western Pennsylvania.
The Weaver Social History Collection contains correspondence, memorabilia, and publications of organizations devoted to these causes. The collection represents groups that Weaver was actively involved such as the Hungry Club, which contains a voluminous amount of correspondence from 1913 to 1951; University Extension Service; Council for Peace and Social Action; Joint Committee on the Social Crisis; League for Social Justice; American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU); and the Allegheny Roundtable. This collection also contains John C. Weaver's personal correspondence.
The Weaver Social History Collection is only minimally processed. Many series have retained the original order of the creator, John C. Weaver, and is not organized chronologically or by subject. The Assorted Publications and Allegheny Roundtable series contain only a box level inventory. Each series is further described in the scope and content notes for that series.
Biography
John C. Weaver was a peace activist devoted to promoting social justice. He documented these important issues in regards to Pittsburgh's and Western Pennsylvania's history, along with activism in the social and political scene. John C. Weaver was born in Rochester, Pennsylvania in 1896. He was raised in a Methodist household and his father was a minister. Weaver received his education at Allegheny College in Meadville, Pennsylvania where he majored in Latin and Greek. Soon after graduating, he joined the U.S. Medical Corps in 1917 and served in France during World War I. After returning from the war in 1920 Weaver moved to Pittsburgh and became a social worker. His first employment in Pittsburgh was as an assistant director of the Kingsley Settlement House in East Liberty. He was employed as a social worker who helped Italian-Americans move and settle in Pittsburgh. It was here that he met and married Elsa Stringaro, an Italian translator at the house.
After being frustrated by the limitations of social work at Kingsley, Weaver joined the Hungry Club in the early 1920s. The Hungry Club, named for its members who were hungry for ideas, as well as ideas, was a public forum in Pittsburgh where people from all backgrounds would meet and discuss the leading issues of the day. Weaver joined as a participator but quickly became the executive director of the club. As executive director, Weaver organized the discussions, panels, and brought in speakers. He chose the topics of discussion, which varied from Pittsburgh politics to animal rights. Although interested in many issues, Weaver mostly advocated for single land tax reform and peace activism. He helped to elect William McNair, Pittsburgh's first single tax mayor of the 1930s. Weaver was also McNair's Secretary of Welfare for a brief time, but resigned because of the "dirty" politics that played out in city hall at that time.
In the late 1940s Weaver helped found the Allegheny Roundtable, a panel discussion program that aired on WQED radio and later became a WQED television program. The Allegheny Roundtable resembled the Hungry Club, as it was a forum to discuss affairs in Pittsburgh and world news. His status in Pittsburgh was heightened during the 1960s because of his opinions of the steel industry, unemployment, and the Vietnam War. In addition, Weaver also wrote a commentary column in the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette and the East Liberty Tribune. He also taught courses at the Henry George School of Social Sciences in New York City as an adjunct professor. Weaver remained active even at the age of 79 when he demonstrated against the Vietnam War during a weekly Vigil for Peace at the Gateway Center in 1973. In addition to his politics, Weaver was a lifelong vegetarian, a Catholic, and an active member of the Society of Friends. Weaver moved from Pittsburgh in the late 1970s to live with his three sons in New York City. He died there in 1985 at the age of 86.
Related Material
Kingsley Association Records, 1894-1980, AIS.1970.05, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Personal papers; Politics; Social action; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Publications; Correspondence; Memorabilia; Newspapers; Pamphlets; Social action -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social workers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Activists; University extension -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Allegheny Roundtable (Television program); Depressions -- 1929 -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Economic conditions; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social conditions; American Civil Liberties Union; League for Social Justice; Joint Committee on the Social Crisis; University Extension Service (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Council for Peace and Social Action; Hungry Club; Weaver, John C.
- Hungry Club, 1913-1951; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The Hungry Club was an organization where people who were "hungry for ideas as well as lunch," could discuss leading issues of the day. John Weaver served as executive director of the Hungry Club. This series contains correspondence, membership lists, scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, and assorted material related to the club. The material in this series is mostly arranged chronologically and contains much of the Hungry Club's correspondence, material related to speakers, membership, and ranges in date from 1913 to 1951.
  - Assorted material relating to its history, purposes and procedures, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Two booklets about the club by Charles C. Cooper, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Analysis of the subject matter of speech topics, 1913-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - List of members, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - List of members, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Membership cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Assorted lists of members, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Receipts, 1919-1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Yearbooks, 1925-1926, 1929-1930, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bank statements and cancelled checks, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Financial statements, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Speaker schedules, 1913-1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Speakers and chairmen, 1913-1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Assorted material relating to speakers, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Attendance at meetings, 1920-1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Speakers, 1931-1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Two speeches about Charles C. Cooper, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Assorted Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Address delivered by Edward H. Jones, Works Progress Administrator for Pennsylvania, December 1935 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, October-December 1913 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence, January, March-June, August, October-December 1914 (Box 2, Folder 4-12)
  - Correspondence, January-May, August-December 1915 (Box 2, Folder 13-22)
  - Correspondence, January-May, August, October-December 1916 (Box 2, Folder 23-31)
  - Correspondence, January- May, October, December 1917 (Box 2, Folder 32-38)
  - Correspondence, January-June, November-December 1918 (Box 2, Folder 39-46)
  - Correspondence, January- May, August-December 1919 (Box 2, Folder 47-56)
  - Correspondence, January-May, September-December 1920 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
  - Correspondence, January-June, September-December 1921 (Box 3, Folder 10-20)
  - Correspondence, January- December 1922 (Box 3, Folder 21-31)
  - Correspondence, January- May, August-December 1923 (Box 3, Folder 32-41)
  - Correspondence, January- May, July- December 1924 (Box 4, Folder 1-11)
  - Correspondence, January-February, May-December 1925 (Box 4, Folder 12-21)
  - Correspondence, January-December 1926 (Box 4, Folder 22-33)
  - Correspondence, January- December 1927 (Box 4, Folder 34-45)
  - Correspondence, January-June, September-October, December 1928 (Box 5, Folder 1-9)
  - Correspondence, January -April, June, September-October, December 1929 (Box 5, Folder 10-21)
  - Correspondence, January-April, July, September 1930 (Box 5, Folder 22-27)
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, October 1930 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Scrapbooks, undated (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks, January 1939- October 1948 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks, 1951-1955 (Box 8, Item 1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1948-1951 (Box 8, Item 2)
  - Card file of speakers, undated (Box 9)
- University Extension Service, II.
  The University Extension Service was an organization for the presentation of low cost public lectures so that everyone may have the opportunity to obtain accurate information on vitally important subjects. The majority of material in this series is further divided into 2 subseries correspondence and club administrative materials. The material in this series ranges in date from 1917 to 1928.
  - Correspondence, 1917-1928; 1.
    This subseries contains correspondence regarding the University Extension Service. The material in this subseries dates from 1917 to 1928 and is organized mostly chronologically.
    - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, January, March-December 1918 (Box 10, Folder 2-12)
    - Correspondence, January- December 1919 (Box 10, Folder 13-24)
    - Correspondence, January- December 1920 (Box 10, Folder 25-34)
    - Correspondence, January-December 1921 (Box 11, Folder 1-12)
    - Correspondence, 1922 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, April - June, September 1924 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, January - July 1925 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, August 1925 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, September 1925 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, October 1925 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, January - May 1926 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, February 1927 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Administrative Materials, 1917-1928; 2.
    This subseries contains assorted administrative materials of the organization, such as, financial information and annual reports. The material dates from 1917 to 1928 and is in the original order of the creator.
    - Members of the Board of Directors, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Receipts for dues, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, March 30, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Secretary's Annual Reports, 1917-1923 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Treasurer's Annual Reports, 1919, 1924-1928 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Season Booklets, 1911-1919 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Season Program Booklets, 1919-1928 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Announcements of Lectures, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper Announcements of Lectures, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Reports of Ticket Sales, 1926-1928 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Notices of Engagements, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Assorted Contracts with Lecturers, 1921-1925 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Contracts with Carnegie Library and Music Hall, 1921-1925 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Pennsylvania Capital Stock Report, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Assorted Bills, undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Assorted Receipts, undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Assorted Photographs, undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Assorted Material, undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Council For Peace And Social Action, 1933-1936; III.
  The Council For Peace and Social Action was considered a central clearing house through which social organizations could pool and exchange ideas. The series contains correspondence of the organization and information on its history and purpose. The material in this series is from 1933 to 1936 and is arranged in somewhat chronological order.
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Statements and proposals, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - History and purpose, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Assorted Materials, Undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Joint Committee on the Social Crisis, 1933; IV.
  The purpose of the Joint Committee on the Social Crisis was to provide a clearing house for religious, civic, and other organizations of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County to deal with problems arising out of the Great Depression. This series contains correspondence, statements and committee proposals, along with the organization's constitution. The material in this series dates from 1933.
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Statements and proposals, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Constitution, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
- League for Social Justice, 1932-1937; V.
  The aim of the League for Social Justice was to "work toward the formulation and realization of a program which will promote social and economic justice." The material in this series includes correspondence of the organization along with information on its history, lectures, and educational programming. The material in this series dates from 1932 to 1937 and retains the arrangement of the collection's creator.
  - Correspondence, April- June 1933 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Data pertaining to its history and purposes, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Constitution, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Ledger, 1933-1937 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, July- September 1933 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, October- December 1933 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1932- 1934, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Lectures, educational programs, and other activities, undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Statements and proposals, undated (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Assorted materials, undated (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Members, undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, January- March 1933 (Box 13, Folder 26)
- John C. Weaver Correspondence, 1916-1950; 1931-1950; VI.
  This series, which contains the correspondence of John C. Weaver regarding the various social causes and organizations of which he was a member. There is also a limited amount of assorted material on addresses and articles written by Weaver. The correspondence in this series dates from 1916 to 1950, with the bulk of the material from 1931 to 1950. The John C. weaver Correspondence series is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1916, 1931-1933 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Article: "What Social Workers Have Been Thinking About," and related correspondence, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1938 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1950 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 14, Folder 7-8)
  - Notes, Talks, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Notes, addresses, and statements, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
- American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), 1931-1941; VII.
  The American Civil Liberties Union's (ACLU) stated mission is "to defend and preserve the individual rights and liberties guaranteed to every person in this country by the Constitution and laws of the United States." The organization works through litigation, legislation, and community education. The material in this series contains the national organization's Bulletins along with clippings and booklets related to the ACLU's mission. Some correspondence related to the Pittsburgh branch is found this series. The dates of the material in the series is from 1931 to 1941. The arrangement of the series retains the original order of the collection's creator.
  - Correspondence with John Weaver, 1931-1935 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Civil Liberties Quarterly, 1931-1932 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Bulletins, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Bulletins, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Bulletins, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Bulletins, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Assorted booklets, undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Assorted newspaper clippings, undated (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Assorted Material, undated (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Bulletins, 1940-1941 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Bulletins, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Pittsburgh branch, Correspondence with John C. Weaver, 1932-1935 (Box 14, Folder 23)
- Assorted Publications and Materials, 1930-1970; VIII.
  The Assorted Publications and Materials series ranges in date from 1930 to 1970, with a majority of material marked as undated. This series contains mainly publications and some correspondence, along with assorted material from organizations interested in economic, social, and labor issues. Most of the material in the Assorted Publications and Materials series is only semi-processed. Boxes 14 to 27 have folder listings, while boxes 28 to 88 are described only to the box level. The Assorted Publications series retains the original order of the collection's creator.
  - Pennsylvania Civil Liberties Committee. Newsletter, 1932 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Pennsylvania Civil Liberties Committee. Assorted Materials, undated (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Pennsylvania Civil Liberties Committee. Names of Members, undated (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - People's Lobby. Membership lists for Pittsburgh, undated (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - People's Lobby. Partial National Membership list, march 1936 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - People's Lobby. Programs and Proposals, undated (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1933 (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 33)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 34)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 35)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 37)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 38)
  - People's Lobby. Correspondence: Benjamin Marsh and John Weaver, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 39)
  - People's Lobby. Bulletin- assorted copies, 1932-1939 (Box 14, Folder 40)
  - People's Lobby. Speech by Gardner Jackson, undated (Box 14, Folder 41)
  - People's Lobby. Speeches by Benjamin Marsh, undated (Box 14, Folder 42)
  - People's Lobby. Assorted Material, undated (Box 14, Folder 43)
  - The Fighting Miner: Organ of the Militant Left Wing Miners of America, December 1933 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Council on Progressive Social Action. Names of Members, 1936 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Council on Progressive Social Action. Memos of Expenses, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Keep America Out of War Committee of the Council on Progressive Social Action, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County. Constitution and Platform, ca.1933 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County. Appeal for support for programs and responses, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County. Pittsburgh Unemployed Organizations: Names of Chairmen, 1930s (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County. National Unemployed League Convention: Speech delivered by A.J. Muste, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County. "The Unemployed in Action: A Challenge to the Unemployed of Pittsburgh", undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County. Assorted Materials, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County. "The Issues Before the Members...", undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Unemployed Citizen's League of Allegheny County. "The Issues Before the Members...", undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Pennsylvania Unemployed League, Allegheny County Division. "Call to the Second Quarterly Convention", undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Pennsylvania Security League, 1930s (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Joint Committee on Unemployment, 1932-1934 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - State Unemployed Convention. Articles of Agreement and Proposals, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Ohio Unemployed League, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Pittsburgh Labor School for Worker's Education, Conducted by the Pennsylvania Unemployed League, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings about relief in Allegheny County and Pittsburgh, 1930s (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Worker's Schools in Western Pennsylvania, 1930s (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Pittsburgh Committee Affiliated Schools for Workers. Assorted Materials, 1930s (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - The Pen and Hammer. Statement of Principles and Program, undated (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - The Pen and Hammer. Calendar of Events, May 1934 (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - The Pen and Hammer. Bulletin, June 1933 (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Technocracy, Inc., Assorted Materials, undated (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Conference for Progressive Labor Action. Assorted Material, undated (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - League for Industrial Democracy. Assorted Materials, undated (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - League for Independent Political Action. Assorted Publications, undated (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - League for Independent Political Action. News Bulletin, April- May, September- October 1932 (Box 15, Folder 29)